Wonder by RJ palasio High School WHAT I ALWAYS loved most about middle school was that it was
separate and different from home. I could go there and be aivia Pullman— —not Via,
which is my name at home. Via was what they called me in elementary school, too.
Back then, everyone knew all about us, of course. Mom used to pick me up after
school, and a August was always in the stroller. There weren’t a lot of people
who were equipped to babysit for Auggie, so Mom and Dad brought him to all my
class plays and concerts and recital all the school functions, the bake sales and
the book fairs. My friends knew him. My friend's parents knew him. My teachers
knew him. The janitor knew him. (“Hey, how you doing Augie he’d always say, and give
August a high five.) August was something of a fixture at
PS22. But in middle school a lot of people didn’t know about August. My old
friends did, of course, but my new friends didn’t. Or if they knew, it wasn’t
necessarily the first thing they knew about me. Maybe it was the second or
third thing they’d hear about me. “Olivia?
Yeah, she’s nice. Did you hear she has a brother who’s
deformed?” I always hated that word word, but I knew it was how people described
Auggie. And I knew those kinds of conversations probably happened all the time out of
earshot, every time I left the room at a party, or bumped into groups of friends
at the pizza place. And that’s okay. I’m
always going to be the sister of a kid with a birth defect: that’s not the issue.
I just don’t always want to be defined that way. The best thing about high
school is that hardly anybody knows me at all. Except Miranda and Ella, of course.
And they know not to go around talking about it. Miranda, Ella, and I have known
each other since the first grade. What’s so nice is we never have to explain
things to one another. When I decided I wanted them to call me Olivia instead of
Via, they got it without my having to explain. They’ve known August since he
was a little baby. When we were little, our favorite thing to do was play dress
up up with Auggie; load him up with feather boas and big hats and Hannah
Montana wigs. He used to love it, of course, and we thought he was adorably
cute in his own way. Ella said he reminded her of ET She didn’t say this
to be mean, of course no maybe it was a
little bit mean). The truth is, there’s a scene in the movie when Drew Barrymore
dresses ET and a blonde wig: and that was a ringer for Auggie and our Miley Cyrus
heyday. Throughout middle school, Miranda, Ella, and I were pretty much our own
little group. Somewhere between super popular and well-liked: not brainy, not jocks, not rich,
not druggies, not mean, not goody goody not huge, not flat. I don’t know if the
three of us found each other because we were so alike and so many ways, or that
because we found each other, we’ve become so alike in so many ways.
We were so happy when we all got into fauler High School. It was such a long
shot that all three of us would be accepted, especially when almost no one
else from our middle school was. I remember how we screamed into our phones
the day we got our acceptance letters. This is why I haven’t understood
what’s been going on with us lately, now that we’re actually in high school. It’s
nothing like how I thought it would be Major Tom OUT OF THE three of us, Miranda had
almost always been the sweetest to August, hugging him and playing with him
long after Ella and I had moved on to playing something else. Even as we got
older, Miranda always made sure to try to include August in our
conversations, ask him how he was doing, talk to him about Avatar or Star Wars or
Bone or something she knew he liked. It was Miranda who had given Auggie the
astronaut helmet he wore practically every day of the year when he was five
or six. She would call him Major Tom and they would sing “Space audity by David
Bowie together. It was their little thing.
They knew all the words and would blast it on the iPod and sing the song out
loud. Since Miranda’s always been really good about calling us as soon as she got
home from summer camp, I was a little surprised when I didn’t hear from her. I
even texted her and she didn’t reply. I figured maybe she had ended up staying
in the camp longer, now that she was a counselor. Maybe she'd met a cute guy.
Then I realized from her Facebook wall that she’d actually been back home for a
full two weeks, so I sent her an I am and
we chatted online a bit, but she didn’t give me a reason for not calling, which I
thought was bizarre. Miranda has always been a little flaky, so I figured that’s
all it was. We made plans to meet me downtown, but then I had to cancel
because we were driving out to visit Tata and Papa for the weekend. So I ended
up not seeing either Miranda or Ella until the first day of school. And, I have
to admit, I was shocked. Miranda looks so different: her hair was cut in this super
cute bob that she dyed bright pink, of all things, and she was wearing a striped
tube top that (a) seemed way inappropriate for school, and (b) was totally not her
usual style. Miranda had always been such a prude about clothes but here she was
all pink-haired and Tube topped But it wasn’t just the way she looked that was
different: she was acting differently, too.
I can’t say she wasn’t nice, because she was, but she seemed kind of distant, like
I was a casual friend. It was the weirdest thing in the
world. At lunch the three of us set together like we always used to, but the
dynamics had shifted. It was obvious to me that Ella and Miranda had gotten
together a few times during the summer without me, though they never actually
said that. I pretended not to be at all upset while we talked, though I could
feel my face getting hot, my smile being fake. Although Ella wasn’t as over the
top as Miranda, I noticed a change in her usual style, too. It’s like they had
talked to each other beforehand about redoing their image at the new school,
but hadn’t bothered to clue me in. I admit: I had always thought I was above
this kind of typical teenage pettiness, but I felt a lump in my throat
throughout lunch. My voice quivered as I said “See you later” when the bell
rang after school I HEAR WE’RE driving you home today.” It was Miranda in eighth
period. She had just sat down at the desk right behind me. I had forgotten that Mom
had called Miranda’s mother the night before to ask if she could drive me home
from school. “You don’t have to,” I answered instinctively, casually. “My mom can pick
me up.” “I thought she had to pick Auggie up or something.” “It turns out she can
pick me up afterward. She just texted me.
Not a problem.” “Oh. Okay.” “Thanks.” It was all a lie on my part, but I
couldn’t see sitting in a car with the new Miranda. After school I ducked into a
restroom to avoid bumping into Miranda’s mother outside. Half an hour later I
walked out of the school, ran the three blocks to the bus stop, hopped on the M86
to Central Park West, and took the subway home. “Hey there, sweetie!” Mom said the
moment I stepped through the front door.
“How was your first day? I was starting to wonder where you guys were.” “We stopped for pizza.”
Incredible how easily a lie can slip through your lips. “Is Miranda not with
you?” She seemed surprised that Miranda wasn’t right behind me. “She went straight
home. We have a lot of homework.” “On your first day?” “Yes, on our first day!” I yelled,
which completely surprised Mom. But before she could say anything, I said:
“School was fine. It’s really big, though.
The kids seem nice.” I wanted to give her a enough information so she wouldn’t
feel the need to ask me more. “How was Augie's first day of school?” Mom
hesitated, her eyebrows still high up on her forehead from when ID snapped at her a second
earlier. “Okay,” she said slowly, like she was letting out of breath. “What do you
mean ‘okay’?” I said. “Was it good or bad?” “He said it was
good.” “So why do you think it wasn’t good?”
“I didn’t say it wasn’t good gez Via,
what’s up with you?” “Just forget I said anything at all,” I answered, and stormed
dramatically into Auggie’s room and slammed the door. He was on his Play
Station and didn’t even look up. I hated how zombified his video games made him.
“So how was school?” I said, scooching Daisy over so I could sit on his bed next to
him. “Fine,” he answered, still not looking up from his game.
“Auggie, I’m talking to you!” I pulled the PlayStation out of his hands. “Hey!” he said
angrily. “How was school?” “I said fine!” he yelled back, grabbing the PlayStation
back from me. “Were people nice to you?” “Yes!” “No one was mean?” He put the PlayStation
down and looked up at me as if I had just asked the dumbest question in the
world. “Why would people be mean?” he said said It was the first time in his life
that I heard him be sarcastic like that.
I didn’t think he had an in him the Padawan Bites the Dust I’M NOT
SURE at what point that night Auggie had cut off his Padawan braid, or why that
made me really mad. I had always found his obsession with everything Star Wars
kind of geeky, and that braid in the back of his hair, with its little beads, was
just awful. But he had always been so proud of it and how long it took him to
grow it and how he had chosen the beads himself in a craft store in Soho. He and
Christopher, his best friend, used to play with lightsabers and Star Wars stuff
whenever they got together, and they had both started growing their braids at the
same time. When August cut his braid off that night, without an explanation,
without telling me beforehand (which was surprising)— )—or even calling Christopher— —I
was just so upset I can’t even explain why. I’ve seen Auggie brushing his hair
in the bathroom mirror. He meticulously tries to get every hair in place. He
tilts his head to look at himself from different angles, like there’s some magic
perspective inside the mirror that could change the dimensions of his face. Mom
knocked on my door after dinner. She looked drained, and I realized that
between me and Auggie, today had been a tough day for her, too.
“So you want to tell me what’s up?” she asked nicely,
softly. “Not now, okay?” I answered. I was reading. I was tired. Maybe later I’d be
up to telling her about Miranda, but not now. “I’ll check in before you go to bed,”
she said, and then she came over and kissed me on the top of my head. “Can
Daisy sleep with me tonight?” “Sure, I’ll bring her in later.” “Don’t forget to come
back back I said as she left. “I promise.” But she didn’t come back that night. Dad
did. He told me Auggie had had a bad first day and Mom was helping him
through it. He asked me how my day had gone and I told him fine. He said he
didn’t believe me for a second, and I told him Miranda and Ella were acting
like jerks. (I didn’t mention how I took the subway home by myself, though.) He said
nothing test friendship like high school, and then proceeded to poke fun at the
fact that I was reading War and Peace Not real fun, of course, since I’d heard
him brag to people that he had a 15-year-old who was reading
Tolstoy.” But he liked to rib me about
where I was in the book, in a war part or
in a peace part, and if there was anything in there about Napoleon’s days
as a hip-hop dancer. It was silly stuff, but Dad always managed to make everyone
laugh. And sometimes that’s all you need to feel better.
“Don’t be mad at Mom,” he said as he bent
down to give me a good night kiss. “You know how much she worries about Augie I
know,” I acknowledged. “Want the light on or off? It’s getting kind of late,” he said,
pausing by the light switch at the door.
“Can you bring Daisy in first 2 seconds later he came back with Daisy dangling
in his arms, and he later down next to me on the bed. “Good night, sweetheart,” he said,
kissing my forehead. He kiss Daisy on her forehead, too. “Good night girly Sweet
dreams an apparition at the door ONCE, I GOT up in the middle of the night
because I was thirsty, and I saw Mom standing outside Auggie’s room. Her hand
was on the door knob her forehead leaning on the door, which was a jar She
wasn’t going in his room or stepping out: just standing right outside the door, as
if she was listening to the sound of his breathing as he slept.
The hallway lights were out. The only thing illuminating her was the blue
NightLight in August’s bedroom. She looked ghostlike standing there. Or maybe
I should say angelic. I tried to walk back into my room without disturbing her,
but she heard me and walked over to me. “Is Augie okay?” I asked. I knew that
sometimes he would wake up choking on his own saliva if he accidentally turned over on his back.
“Oh, he’s fine,” she said, wrapping her arms around me. She walked me back into my
room, pulled the covers over me, and kiss me good night. She never explained what
she was doing outside his door, and I never asked. I wonder how many nights she
stood outside his door. And I wonder if she’s ever stood outside my door like that
[Music]